It's a great honor today
إنه لشرف عظيم اليوم
to share with you
أن أقدم لكم
The Digital Universe,
الكون الرقمي،
which was created for humanity
الذي تم صنعه للبشرية
to really see where we are
حتى يروا حقيقة أين نحن
in the universe.
في الكون.
And so I think we can roll the video that we have.
أعتقد أنه يمكننا أن نشغل الفيديو الذي لدينا.
[The Himalayas.]
[الهيمالايا.]
(Music)
(موسيقى)
The flat horizon that we've evolved with
كارتر إمارت: الأفق المسطح الذي نمونا معه
has been a metaphor for the
كان دومًا رمزًا
infinite: unbounded resources
للموارد غير المحدودة واللانهائية
and unlimited capacity
والسعة اللامحدودة
for disposal of waste.
للتخلص من النفايات.
It wasn't until we really
لم يكن حتى حقيقة
left Earth,
تركنا الأرض،
got above the atmosphere
علونا فوق الغلاف الجوي
and had seen the horizon
ورأينا الأفق
bend back on itself,
ينثني حول نفسه
that we could understand our planet
حتى استطعنا أن نفهم كوكبنا
as a limited condition.
كحالة محدودة.
The Digital Universe Atlas
الأطلس الرقمي للكون
has been built
تم بناؤه
at the American Museum of Natural History
في المتحف الأمريكي للتاريخ الطبيعي
over the past 12 years.
على مدى الـ١٢ سنة الماضية.
We maintain that,
لقد حافظنا على هذا،
put that together
وجمعناه سويًا
as a project
كمشروع
to really chart the universe
لرسم خريطة الكون
across all scales.
عبر كل المقاييس.
What we see here are satellites around the Earth
ما نراه هنا هي أقمارًا إصطناعية حول الأرض،
and the Earth in proper registration
والأرض في تسجيل ملائم
against the universe, as we see.
مقارنة بالكون، كما نرى.
NASA supported this work
لقد دعمت ناسا هذا العمل
12 years ago
منذ ١٢ عاما
as part of the rebuilding
كجزء من إعادة بناء
of the Hayden Planetarium
القبة السماوية هايدن
so that we would share this with the world.
بحيث نتيح هذا للعالم.
The Digital Universe is the basis
الكون الرقمي هو الأساس
of our space show productions that we do --
لما ننتجه من برامج وعروض عن الفضاء--
our main space shows in the dome.
عروضنا الرئيسية عن الفضاء في القبة.
But what you see here
ولكن ما ترونه هنا
is the result of, actually, internships
هو حقيقة نتاج تدريب داخلي
that we hosted with Linkoping University
قمنا باستضافته بالتعاون مع جامعة لينكوبينج
in Sweden.
في السويد.
I've had 12 students work on this
لقد كان لدي ١٢ طالبًا يشاركون في هذا العمل
for their graduate work,
لدراساتهم العليا.
and the result has been this software called Uniview
وكانت النتيجة هي هذا البرنامج الذي سمي "يونيفيو"
and a company called SCISS in Sweden.
وشركة اسمها إس سي أي إس إس في السويد.
This software
هذا البرنامج
allows interactive use,
يدعم الاستخدام التفاعلي.
so this actual flight path
فهذا المسار الفعلي للرحلة
and movie that we see here
والفيلم الذي نراه هنا
was actually flown live.
تم بالفعل تصويره حيا.
I captured this live from my laptop
لقد التقطت هذا حيا عبر حاسبي المحمول
in a cafe called Earth Matters
في مقهى اسمه شؤون الأرض
on the Lower East Side of Manhattan, where I live,
على الجانب الأسفل من شرق مانهاتن، حيث أسكن.
and it was done
ولقد تم القيام به
as a collaborative project
كمشروع تعاوني
with the Rubin Museum of Himalayan Art
مع متحف روبين لفن الهيمالايا
for an exhibit
لمعرض عن
on comparative cosmology.
علم الكونيات المقارن.
And so as we move out,
وفيما ننطلق للخارج
we see continuously from our planet
نطالع بشكل متواصل من كوكبنا
all the way out into the realm of galaxies, as we see here,
خارجين إلى حقيقة المجرات كما نرى هنا،
light-travel time, giving you a sense of how far away we are.
زمن انتقال الضوء، يعطيك فكرة عن كم نحن بعيدين.
As we move out,
ونحن نتحرك للخارج،
the light from these distant galaxies
الضوء من هذه المجرات البعيدة
have taken so long,
استغرق وقتا طويلا،
we're essentially backing up into the past.
نحن أساسًا نتراجع في الماضي.
We back so far up
نتراجع كثيرًا
we're finally seeing a containment around us --
وأخيرًا نرى شيئًا يحتوينا--
the afterglow of the Big Bang.
شفق الانفجار الكبير
This is the WMAP
هذاهو ما يخص بعثة دبليو إم إيه بي
microwave background
من خلفية إشعاعية
that we see.
هذا الذي نراه.
We'll fly outside it here, just to see this sort of containment.
سنحلق خارجه فقط لنرى هذا الاحتواء.
If we were outside this,
لو كنا خارج هذه،
it would almost be meaningless, in the sense as before time.
لأصبح تقريبًا عديم المعنى، مقارنة بما قبل ذلك.
But this our containment of the visible universe.
ولكن هذا هو احتواؤنا للمرئي من الكون.
We know the universe is bigger than that which we can see.
نحن نعلم أن الكون أكبر مما نستطيع أن نراه.
Coming back quickly,
نعود بسرعة،
we see here the radio sphere that we jumped out of in the beginning,
نرى هنا المجال الإشعاعي الذي قفزنا منه في البداية.
but these are positions,
ولكن هذه مواضع،
the latest positions of exoplanets
أحدث مواضع لكواكب خارج المجموعة الشمسية
that we've mapped,
التي رسمناها على الخريطة.
and our sun here, obviously, with our own solar system.
وهنا شمسنا بالطبع مع نظامنا الشمسي.
What you're going to see -- we're going to have to jump in here pretty quickly
ما سترونه-- سيتوجب عليكم أن تقفزوا هنا بسرعة
between several orders of magnitude
بين ارتفاعات مختلفة
to get down to where we see the solar system --
حتى تصلوا إلى حيث نرى النظام الشمسي.
these are the paths of
هذه هي مسارات
Voyager 1, Voyager 2, Pioneer 11 and Pioneer 10,
فوياجر ١ وفوياجر ٢ وبيونير ١١ وبيونير ١٠،
the first four spacecraft to have left the solar system.
أول أربعة مكوكات فضائية غادرت النظام الشمسي.
Coming in closer,
نقترب،
picking up Earth,
نختار الأرض.
orbit of the Moon, and we see the Earth.
مدار القمر، ونرى الأرض.
This map can be updated,
هذه الخريطة يمكن تحديثها.
and we can add in new data.
ويمكننا إضافة بيانات جديدة.
I know Dr. Carolyn Porco is the camera P.I.
أنا أعرف د. كارولاين بوركو الباحثة الرئيسية للكاميرا
for the Cassini mission.
لبعثة كاسيني.
But here we see the complex trajectory
ولكن هنا نرى المسار المعقد
of the Cassini mission
لبعثة كاسيني
color coded for different mission phases,
تم تلوينه للتعبير عن المراحل المختلفة للبعثة،
ingeniously developed so that
مطور ببراعة بحيث أن
45 encounters with the largest moon, Titan,
45 التقاء مع تايتن وهو أكبر قمر
which is larger that the planet Mercury,
وهو أكبر من الكوكب عطارد،
diverts the orbit into different parts of mission phase.
تحول المدار إلى الأجزاء المختلفة لمراحل البعثة.
This software allows us to come close
هذا البرنامج يمكننا من الاقتراب
and look at parts of this.
والنظر إلى أجزاء من هذا.
This software can also be networked between domes.
هذا البرنامج أيضًا يمكن توصيله شبكيًا بين القباب.
We have a growing user base of this,
لدينا قاعدة متنامية ممن يستخدمونه.
and we network domes.
ونقوم بربط القباب شبكيًا.
And we can network between domes and classrooms.
ويمكننا الربط بين القباب وقاعات الدراسة.
We're actually sharing tours of the universe
نحن حقيقة نشارك رحلات الكون
with the first sub-Saharan
مع أول قبة سماوية جنوب الصحراء الكبرى
planetarium in Ghana
في غانا
as well as
وأيضًا
new libraries that have been built
مع مكتبات جديدة تم تأسيسها
in the ghettos in Columbia
في الأحياء الفقيرة في كولومبيا
and a high school
ومدرسة ثانوية
in Cambodia.
في كمبوديا.
And the Cambodians have
ولقد قام الكمبوديين
actually controlled the Hayden Planetarium from their high school.
حقيقة بالتحكم في قبة هايدن من مدرستهم الثانوية.
This is an image from Saturday,
هذه صورة ليوم السبت،
photographed by the Aqua satellite, but through the Uniview software.
التقطت بالقمر الصناعي أكوا ، ولكن باستخدام برنامج اليونيفيو.
So you're seeing the edge of the Earth.
وهكذا فأنتم ترون حافة الأرض.
This is Nepal.
هذه نيبال.
This is, in fact, right here is the valley of Lhasa,
هذا، حقيقة، هنا وادي لاسا،
right here in Tibet.
هنا في التبت.
But we can see the haze
ولكن يمكننا رؤية الغبار
from fires and so forth in the Ganges valley
المنبعث من الحرائق وهكذا حتى وادي نهر الجانج
down below in India.
إلى الأسفل في الهند.
This is Nepal and Tibet.
هذه نيبال والتبت.
And just in closing,
وفي الختام،
I'd just like to say this beautiful world that we live on --
أريد أن أقول أن هذا العالم الرائع الذي نعيش فيه--
here we see a bit of the snow
هنا نرى بعض الجليد
that some of you may have had to brave in coming out --
لربما كان بعضكم لديه الجرأة للخروج.
so I'd like to just say
وهكذا فأنا أريد أن أقول
that what the world needs now
أن ما يحتاجه العالم الآن
is a sense of being able to
هو التفكير في أن نكون قادرين
look at ourselves in this much larger condition now
على أن ننظر لأنفسنا في هذه الحالة الأوسع كثيرا الآن
and a much larger sense of what home is.
والتفكير بشكل أوسع في معنى ما هو الوطن.
Because our home is the universe,
لأن وطننا هو الكون،
and we are the universe, essentially.
ونحن الكون، في الأساس.
We carry that in us.
نحن نحمل هذا في أنفسنا.
And to be able to see our context
وأن نستطيع أن نرى محيطنا
in this larger sense at all scales
بهذا الشكل الأكبر بكل المقاييس
helps us all, I think, in understanding
سيساعدنا جميعًا، فيما أعتقد، على فهم
where we are and who we are in the universe.
أين نحن ومن نحن في هذا الكون.
Thank you.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)